Central New York Transportation Collection
Central New York Transportation Collection
1801-1906
0.25 linear ft.
Collection of ephemera relating to transportation in and around central New York (Erie Canal, railroads, etc)
2692100
Biographical History
Central New York (often abbreviated "CNY") is a term used to broadly describe the central region of New York State, roughly including the counties of Cayuga, Cortland, Madison, Oneida, Onondaga, Oswego, Tompkins, and Herkimer. Towns, villages and cities in the area include Auburn, Cortland, Oneida, Rome, Sherrill, Utica, Syracuse, Fulton, Oswego, Ithaca, Cazenovia, and Seneca Falls. The Central New York Military Tract, land reserved from soldiers of the American Revolution, was located here, and many towns derived from the tracts have classical names.
The borders of Central New York are not precisely defined, however. The core of the region consists of Onondaga County, Cayuga County, Oswego County and Madison County. Tompkins County and Cortland County are often considered part of New York's "Southern Tier" region, while Oneida County and Herkimer County are often considered part of the "Mohawk Valley" region.
In 2009 the region had a population of about 1.1 million.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Central New York Transportation Collection is divided into three series: canals, railroads, and roads.
Canals contains photographs and miscellaneous. Miscellaneous consists of business records, correspondence, and a newspaper.
Railroads contains photographs and miscellaneous. Miscellaneous consists of business records, correspondence, and an oversized poster.
Roads consists of miscellaneous items such as correspondence and business records.
Arrangement of the Collection
Items are arranged in chronological order with undated material at the end of the folder.
Related Material
has numerous collections relating to local history. For a complete list, please refer to the. In particular, see also the
Central New York Trade Catalogs and Business Ephemera
,
Central New York Cultural Ephemera
, and
Central New York Local History
collections. There are also a number of collections relating to railroads in the Northeast; please refer to for a full listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Railroads; Corning, Erastus, 1794-1872; First Company of the Great Western Turnpike Road.; Canals -- New York (State); Chenango Turnpike Road (N.Y.); Roads -- New York (State); Tariff -- Law and legislation.; Toll roads -- New York (State); Transportation -- New York (State); Albion (Orleans County, N.Y.) -- History.; Camden (N.Y.) -- History.; Chenango (N.Y.) -- History.; Rochester (N.Y.) -- History.; Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); Newspapers.; Petitions.; Stock certificates.; Stereographs.; Photographs.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, various.
Accruals
Additions at irregular intervals.
Inventory
- Canals
  - Photographs, undated; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1815-1866 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1849; newspaper (Map-case 102)
- Railroads
  - Photographs, undated; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1854-1906; undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1868; poster (Map-case 102)
- Roads
  - Miscellaneous, 1801-1810; undated (Box 1)